Homosexuality/LGBT Collection
Sophia Smith Collection
Homosexuality/LGBT collection
1932-2011
1970-1978
MS 395
9 boxes (3.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
This collection consists of printed materials that document the evolution of attitudes and approaches to lesbian, gay, and bisexual people and organizations from 1932-1995 (mostly the 1970s), and documents the political struggles of lesbians, gay men, and bisexuals to oppose homophobic discrimination in U.S. society. Also of interest are numerous newsletters, periodicals and leaflets that document lesbian organizing in Western Massachusetts.
The Homosexuality/LGBT Collection consists of articles, books, leaflets, newsletters, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, periodicals and position papers that document the evolution of legal, medical, political, individual and public attitudes and approaches to lesbian, gay, and bisexual people and organizations from 1932 to the present. There are only a few items dating from the period before Stonewall (1969), including a review of the 1932 German film "Maedchen in Uniform" from Literary Digest; psychiatrist Frank Caprio's 1954 book, Female Homosexuality: A Psychodynamic Study; and the Scottish Home Department's 1957 Report of the Committee on Homosexual Offences and Prostitution. Without exception these publications reflect the predominant assumptions about the pathological nature of homosexual identity and behavior that characterize the period before the emergence of the gay liberation movement.
The vast majority of the items in the collection date from 1970 to 1978. These document the discursive and political struggles that surrounded the efforts of lesbians, gay men, and bisexuals to oppose the medicalization and criminalization of homosexuality and to oppose homophobic discrimination at every level of U.S. society. Some of this material reflects conservatives' efforts to oppose gay liberation struggles and some demonstrates the widespread confusion and ambivalence about lesbians and gay men shared by mainstream journalists, politicians, and medical and legal professionals during the 1970s. Most of the material, however, documents lesbian, gay and bisexual efforts to raise public consciousness about same-sex sexuality and demonstrates the gradual inroads made by the gay and lesbian liberation movement during the decade of the 1970s, especially in college and university settings. Newspapers such as The Militant and The Village Voice are particularly well-represented among the newspaper clippings in the collection. Also of interest are numerous newsletters, periodicals and leaflets that document lesbian organizing in the Pioneer Valley and surrounding areas.
The collection is open to reseach according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Multiple donors have contributed to this subject collection.
Periodic additions are expected.
Gay liberation movement--History--20th century--Sources; Gay rights--History--20th century--Sources; Gays--Periodicals; Gender identity--History--20th century--Sources; Homosexuality--Psychological aspects--History--20th century--Sources; Lesbian feminism--History--Sources; Lesbians--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Lesbians--Periodicals; Lesbians in literature
- General, 1964-81, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- General: Connecticut River Valley of Massachusetts, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Newspaper clippings, 1932, 1965, 1971-81 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
- Papers and pamphlets
  - General, 1973-87, undated (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
  - Alice, Gordon, Debbie, and Mary, "Lesbian Separatism: An Amazon Analysis," 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Leana Furgeri, "The Lesbian Feminist Movement and Social Change: Female Homosociality, a New Consciousness," PhD thesis, Teacher's College, Columbia University, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9-12)
  - "Report of the Committee on Homosexual Offences and Prostitution," Scotland, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Aging, 1982-2010 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Conferences, 1975, 1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- "Dyke Sex Calendar 1990" Dykes on the Wall Productions, Vancouver, BC, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Film and video, 1981-88, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Health, 1974-79, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Lesbian history
  - General, 1975-79 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Travelling Lesbians or Sisters on the Road" by Birdie MacLennon, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Literature
  - General, 1975-78, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bibliographies (Box 2)
    - General, 1959-79, undated (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
    - "Checklist of lesbian, variant and homosexual fiction in English or available in English translation" by Marion Zimmer Bradley and Gene Damon, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Checklist supplement" by Marion Zimmer Bradley and Gene Damon, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Astra's Tower" checklist of lesbian literature by Marion Zimmer Bradley, Special leaflet 3 and 5, 1959, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Book stores and catalogs
    - General, 1975-89, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Elysian Fields, Booksellers, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Independent Woman Books, 1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Lambda Rising, Whole Gay Catalog, 1984-86 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Oscar Wilde Memorial Bookshop, 1988-89, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Organizations
  - General, 1966-78, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Daughters of Bilitis, 1964-71, undated, [see also Periodicals] (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Gay Flames: pamphlets 1-4, 7-13, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Lesbian Avengers, 1993-94, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Lesbians for Lesbians, circa 1991 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - National Gay Task Force/National Gay and Lesbian Task Force, 1974-88, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - National Organization for Women, 1973-80, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Radicalesbians, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Survey: Violence Against S/M Women Within the Lesbian Community (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Transgenderism, 1996, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Transexualism, 1971, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Periodicals, [see also oversize box and SSC Periodicals Collection]
  - Changes, Minneapolis, no. 17, Jul 1971 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - The Closet Door! Newsletter of the Student Homophile League of the University of Massachusetts Amherst, 1971-72, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Come Out Comix, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Coming Out Rage: a Feminist Journal for Lesbians/Produced by Lesbian Feminists/DOB, May 1973 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Dykes and Gorgons; Dyke Doings; Dynamite Damsels (comic book), May-June 1973; Jan 1976; undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Gay Activist; Gay Men's Liberation and last motive, June 1973 and 1972 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Gay People and Mental Health; Gossip: a Journal of Lesbian Feminist Ethics, 1973 and 1986 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Labyris, fall 1978-winter 1979 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Lambda Rising Book Report V.1 No 5-7; Lambda Rising News, 1988 and 1984-86 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - The Leaping Lesbian V.3 No.2; Lesbian Ethics V. 4 No.1, undated, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - A Lesbian Position; Lesbians Rising; Long Time Coming; LVA: Lesbian Visual Artists Newsletter, 1983-1986, May/Jun 1976, Apr/May 1976, spr 1995 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Mauve Messages; Motive (lesbian/feminist issue), Jul/Aug 1975, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Multicultural Jewish Dyke Newsletter, 1992-93 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Old Maid; One: The Homosexual Magazine issue, "The Feminine Viewpoint"; Out in Comics, Spring 1975, Feb 1954, 2002-2003 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Prism Comics; Purple Rage, 2003, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - The Wishing Well; Witch Dream, Matriarchal Comix, Amazon Reality Collective; Womanspace News, spr 1978, undated, May/Jun 1986 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Books
  - Aalfs, Janet et al editors, Tuesday Night: poetry and fiction by Valley Lesbian Writers Group, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Brown, Rita Mae. A Plain Brown Wrapper, Diana Press, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Caprio, Frank S., M.D. Female Homosexuality: A Psychodynamic Study of Lesbianism, Citadel Press, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Chideckel, Maurice. F emale Sex Perversion: The Sexually Aberrated Woman as She Is, Eugenics Publishing Co., 1938 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Cottingham, Laura, lesbians are so chic…that we are not really lesbians at all, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Covina, Gina and Laurel Galana, editors. The Lesbian Reader: an Amazon Quarterly Anthology, Amazon Press,1975 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Dykewoman, Elana. They Will Know Me By My Teeth: stories and poems of lesbian struggle, celebration, and survival, Megaera Press, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Gaia's Guide, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Gearhart, Sally. The Feminist Tarot: A View from the Dykes, Pandora's Boox, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Grahn, Judy. Edward the Dyke and other poems, Women's Press Collective, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Kissen, Rita M. The Last Closet, Heinemann, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Lesbians Speak Out, Women's Press Collective, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Louÿs, Pierre, Les Chansons de Bilitis, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Myron, Nancy and Charlotte Bunch. Lesbianism and the Women's Movement, Diana Press, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Nachman, Elana, "Riverfinger Woman: a novel": typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 8-10)
  - Norday, Michael. Warped, Beacon, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Palm of Your Hand: a collection of writings and drawings by lesbians from Baltimore and elsewhere, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Portland Women's Center, Opening, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - S.C.U.M. (Society for Cutting Up Men), Woman to Woman: a book of poems and drawings by women, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Sue, Nelly, Dian, Carol, Billie. Country Lesbians: The Story of the Womanshare Collective, WomanShare Books, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Stewart-Park, Angela and Cassidy, Jules, We're Here: Conversations with Lesbian Women, Quartet Books Ltd., 1977 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Thunder from the Earth, Lavender Press, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Vida, Ginny, editor. Our Right to Love: a lesbian resource book, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Oversize Materials
  - D.Y.K.E. (Do You Know Enough), a lesbian game compiled by Flowing (Margaret Johnson), Julia Penelope, Sue Stepanek, and Sarah Valentine, LipService, Inc., 1986 (Box 8)
  - Literature: Alyson Lesbian & Feminist Book Catalog, fall-winter 1984 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Organizations: "Read This Queers" published anonymously by Queers; "Radicalesbians/GLF Women," undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Periodicals
    - Lambda Rising Book Report, Vol I, no. 4,6,7,8,9,10,111988-89 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Wicce: A Lesbian/Feminist Newspaper, Pennsylvania, summer 1975 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Lesbian rights banner and poster, undated (Map-case Flat file dwr 3)
  - Gay Liberation Front: poster, undated (Box F)
  - Lesbian Avengers: miscellaneous, 1993-94, undated (Box F)